<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Calendar of State Papers, Colonial Series, America and West Indies, 1669 - 1674</title>
        <editor>W. Noel Sainsbury</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Longmans, H.M.S.O.</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date when="1889" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Derived from the Internet Archive version</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <geoDecl xml:id="WGS" datum="WGS84">World Geodetic System</geoDecl>
      
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <place xml:id="ja">
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      
      <div>
        <head>
          <hi rend="sc">
            Colonial Papers.<lb/>
            America and West Indies.
          </hi>
        </head>
        <p> Memorial of the Spanish Ambassador to King Charles II. Reresents that the answer of Sec.
          Lord Arlington and Sec. Trevor to London, his paper of <date when="1669-08-08">8th
            August</date> concerning hostilities committed by his Majesty's subjects of <placeName>Jamaica<geo decls="#wgs"></geo></placeName> is
          so different from what has been promised, that he is obliged to demand what was agreed
          upon in writing, and cannot determine upon the expedients offered till he receives orders
          from his Queen. But the truth of the account he gave his Majesty on the <date
            when="1669-12-12">12th December</date> last of a new incursion of his Majesty's subjects
          of Jamaica upon Puerto Bello, pillaging and committing outrages scarce heard of, being now
          confirmed by the George and Samuel from Jamaica, by whose bills of lading it appears that
          besides what George Potts and other merchants received of plate, the share of every
          soldier was 600 (oz.) or 80l. at half a crown an ounce, whence it may be guessed what
          quantity the officers, Governor, and their confidants had; the Ambassador desires that his
          Queen may have full satisfaction, and the Governor of Jamaica the punishment due for an
          incursion so unjust and contrary to the faith of the new Treaty of the general peace. And
          as other vessels are arrived with part of the booty, and the number of ships designed for
          Jamaica is increased, he desires that just restitution be made, and convenient orders
          given for the future. <hi rend="ital">Annexed,</hi>
        </p>
        <list>
          <item>
            <p>"The Spanish Ambassador's paper" [above referred to as delivered on 12th December
              last]. Being an account of what happened at the taking of Puerto Bello by the English
              of Jamaica under the command of John Doglar, which account he sent to Havre de Grace :
              On <date whem="1668-10-20">10-20 June 1668</date> we landed at Puerto Belo with 422
              men in 28 canoes, leaving our ships 37 leagues off the west coast. On 11th we advanced
              to the walls of Fort St. James, where were 30 pieces of artillery. After three or four
              hours hard fighting we assaulted the fort and made ourselves masters of the garrison,
              all of which refusing quarter were either killed, wounded, or cut to pieces. The next
              day we attacked Fort St. Philip, on the other side of the coast, where were 12 pieces
              of artillery, and after fighting three or four hours it surrendered. After remaining
              some <pb/>days in said fort sickness broke out among our troops, of which we lost half
              by sickness and fighting, so that we were obliged to abandon these places and received
              100,000 crowns from the Spaniards for retiring. Had we had 800 men we might have gone
              to Panama, about 18 leagues to the south of Puerto Velo, and have easily made
              ourselves masters of it, as also of the Kingdom of Peru. The chiefs of the Expedition
              were Henry Morgan, Commander-in-Chief, John Doglar, Julian John Salter, Enoch Clarke,
              Capt. Rudolph Court, Colliar, John James, Maurice. French. Together 3 pp. [Col.
              Papers, Vol. XXIV., Nos. 1-2.] </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>Mem. " Your Honor" [? Under Sec. Williamson] is desired to request of the King a
              supply of fire arms and ammunition for the Somers Islands, also a convoy for the Comp.
              magazine ship, John Jenkins, Commander. Governor Sir John Hey don arrived at the
              Bermudas on 1 6th May 1669, in the magazine ship, Capt. John Jenkins. Lefroy, II. 286.
              \ p. [Col. Papers, Vol. XXIV., No. 3.] </p>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>