<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Calendar of State Papers: Colonial Series</title>
        <editor>W. Noel Sansbury</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <geoDecl xml:id="WGS" datum="WGS84">WGS84</geoDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <!-- use the iso 3166 country codes + other for towns
          http://userpage.chemie.fu-berlin.de/diverse/doc/ISO_3166.html
        -->
        <place xml:id="us_ne" type="region">
          <placeName>New England</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="indies" type="region">
          <placeName>West Indies</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="en" type="region">
          <placeName>England</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="gb" type="region">
          <placeName>Great Britain</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="pl" type="region">
          <placeName>Poland</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="ru" type="region">
          <placeName>Russia</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="es" type="region">
          <placeName>Spain</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="ag" type="colony">
          <placeName>Antigua</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="bb" type="colony">
          <placeName>Barbados</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="jm" type="colony">
          <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="ca_nl" type="colony">
          <placeName>Newfoundland</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="ca_ns" type="colony">
          <placeName>Nova Scotia</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me" type="colony">
          <placeName>Maine</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_nh" type="colony">
          <placeName>New Hampshire</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_ma" type="colony">
          <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_sc" type="colony">
          <placeName>South Carolina</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_nc" type="colony">
          <placeName>North Carolina</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="ca_ns_annapolis_royal" type="colony">
          <placeName>Annapolis Royal</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me_frederick" type="place">
          <placeName>Fort Frederick</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me_pemaquid" type="place">
          <placeName>Pemaquid</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me_newharbor" type="place">
          <placeName>New Harbor</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me_york" type="place">
          <placeName>York</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me_portland" type="place">
          <placeName>Portland</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me_norridgewock" type="place">
          <placeName>Norridgewock</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_me_scarborough" type="place">
          <placeName>Scarborough</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_nh_new_castle" type="place">
          <placeName>New Castle</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="us_ma_boston" type="place">
          <placeName>Boston</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="en_london" type="place">
          <placeName>London</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="en_whitehall" type="place">
          <placeName>Whitehall</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="en_southwark" type="place">
          <placeName>Southwark</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="pl_danzig" type="place">
          <placeName>Danzig</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="gf_stlawrence" type="natural">
          <placeName>Gulf of St. Lawrence</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>        
        <place xml:id="rv_stcroix" type="natural">
          <placeName>St. Croix River</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="rv_kennebec" type="natural">
          <placeName>Kennebec River</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="rv_sheepscot" type="natural">
          <placeName>Sheepscot River</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="rv_saco" type="natural">
          <placeName>Saco River</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo></geo>
          </location>
        </place>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>1</num><date when="1731-01-02">Jan. 2</date></dateline>
        <p>H.M. Warrant for appointment of Edward Bertie and John Hammerton, Secretary and Register
          of <placeName ref="#us_sc" role="secondary">S. Carolina</placeName>, for their lives and to be executed by
          them or sufficient Deputies, they having surrendered the grant of the said offices to them
          by the late Lords Proprietors etc. Countersigned, Holies Newcastle. Copy. [C.O. 324. 36.
          pp. 253, 254 ; and 324, 50. pp. 93, 94.]</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>2</num><date when="1731-01-03">Jan. 3</date></dateline>
        <p>Memorial of loss and damage (2704Z. 2s. 2d. sterl.) sustained by Solomon and Elias de Paz
          of <placeName ref="#en_london" role="descriptive">London</placeName>, merchants, owners of the Friendship and
          cargo taken 24th Feb. 1728(9), off <placeName ref="#jm" role="direct">Jamaica</placeName>, by two
          Spanish vessels, on her voyage from <placeName ref="#us_ne" role="indirect">New England</placeName> to
            <placeName ref="#bb" role="indirect">Barbados</placeName> etc. The Friendship was bought and fitted out
          in New England on their account. Signed, Elias de Paz. Endorsed, Reed, (from Elias de Paz)
          22nd Jan., 1731 1 pp. Enclosed, 2. i-viii. Invoice, bill of lading and correspondence
          relating to foregoing. [C.O. 388, 93. Nos. 4, 4 i-viii.]</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>3</num><date when="1731-01-04">Jan. 4</date></dateline>
        <p>H.M. Warrant for using the new Seal of <placeName ref="#us_nc" role="secondary">N. Carolina</placeName>. Countersigned, Holies Newcastle.
          Copy. [C.O. 324, 36. pp. 261, 262.]</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>4</num><date when="1731-01-07">Jan. 7</date></dateline>
        <p>Order of King in Council. Confirming Act of <placeName ref="#jm" role="secondary">Jamaica</placeName> concerning the estate of Thomas King,
          deed. Signed, Temple Stanyan. Endorsed, Reed. 10th, Read 11th
            Aug., 1731. 1J pp. [C.O. 137, 19. ff. 87, 87v., 8Sv.]</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>5</num><date when="1731-01-07">Jan. 7</date></dateline>
        <p>Order of King in Council. Confirming Act of <placeName ref="#ag" role="secondary">Antigua</placeName>, 1729, for cutting off the intail of
          lands formerly of John Bradshaw deed, and settling the same upon Francis Delap of
            Antigua, merchant, etc. Signed, Temple Stanyan. Endorsed, Reed.
          10th, Read llth Aug., 1731. If pp. [C.O. 152, 19. ff. 63, Q7v.]</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>6</num><date when="1731-01-11">Jan. 11</date></dateline>
        <p><placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="secondary">Boston</placeName>. 
        Governor Belcher to the Duke of Newcastle. Since I 
        had the honour of writing you last I have met the Assembly 
        of <placeName ref="#us_ma" role="direct">this Province</placeName> and after recommending to them what I thought 
        needfull for H.M. honour and service, and their own good, and 
        in a more especial manner pressing upon them H.M. 27th 
        Instruction for fixing a salary on me and my successor I waited 
        on them in a session of eighteen dayes, and finding they wou'd         
        come to no amendments on the bill they had past before, I 
        dissolv'd them, and inclose your Grace a Journal of the pro- 
        ceedings at this short session. I have issu'd writts for a new 
        Assembly to meet the 10th of next mo. and hope there will be a 
        change in the Assembly for the better advancing H.M. honour 
        and service, and nothing in my power shall be wanting towards 
        it. But should it be otherwise I think I have done but my 
        duty in dissolving the late Assembly since they would come 
        no nearer to the King's Instruction, etc. Repeats recommendation 
        of Mr. Sherburn for Lt. Gov. of <placeName ref="#us_nh" role="descriptive">N.H.</placeName> v. Dec. 15, 1730. On 
        24th Dec. received Additional Instruction of Sept. 26th for the 
        better preservation of H.M. woods and issued Proclamations 
        in both Provinces accordingly. Continues : This day I receiv'd 
        from Col. Dunbar H.M. Order in Council, 12th Nov., mentioning 
        a representation that I was preparing a military expedition 
        against <placeName ref="#us_me_frederick" role="direct">Frederick's fort</placeName> etc. Continues : In this representation 
        my Lord Duke there is not the shadow of truth, nor did I ever 
        make the least attempt or preparation of that nature. Yet I 
        am not at all surpriz'd that Col. Dunbar had the folly, and 
        confidence as well as malice to make such a representation 
        against me. Because I am lately told he has wrote many other 
        palpable falshoods to do me all the hurt in his power, but if he 
        would confine himself to truth I should not give myself any 
        trouble about him : the ship by which this goes sails in the 
        morning, that I shall not be able to send your Grace the necessary 
        papers of a notorious riott committed by some people belonging 
        to Frederick's fort on some of H.M. subjects of this Province, 
        as also what I directed H.M. Lt. Govr. of this Province to 
        do at <placeName ref="#us_me_pemaquid" role="direct">Pemaquid</placeName> upon a visitation I order'd him to make to all 
        the fortifications of this Province. Another ship will sail in a 
        few dayes by which I shall send these things for my justification, 
        and which I believe will be to the intire satisfaction of H.M. 
        and his Ministers, and convince your Grace with what injustice 
        this gentleman has treated me. If he intends to take upon 
        him the office of an informer upon all my actions, and then to 
        present them in a false light, it will be giving your Grace and the 
        rest of H.M. Ministers a vast deal of unnecessary trouble. I 
        should be glad when he seeks to make any complaints against 
        me for the future that he would serve me with a copy before 
        he sends them away, then my answer might go in the same 
        ship, and had he done so now, I presume there had been no 
        occasion for H.M. order to me of 12th Nov., the matter on which 
        it is founded being absolutely false. I ask pardon for giving 
        your Grace so great an interruption from the vast affairs of 
        Europe, that ingross your precious hours etc. Signed, J. Belcher. 
        4 pp. Enclosed, </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>6.1</num><date when="1731-01-11">Jan. 11</date></dateline>
        <p>Copy of proceedings of the General Court of the 
          <placeName ref="#us_ma" role="direct">Massachusetts Bay</placeName>, Sept., Oct., 1730, relating to a 
          riot at <placeName ref="us_me_newharbor" role="direct">New Harbour</placeName>, near Pemaquid, in York County,
          upon the complaint of Josiah Grover against some 
          Irish settlers, who seized him and his fishing schooner 
          and company when he went to clear and settle some 
          land there purchased by his ancestor, John Brown, 
          from the Indians 15th July, 1625. He escaped to 
          <placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="direct">Boston</placeName> and complains to the Governor, who instructed 
          the Justices of <placeName ref="#us_me_york" role="indirect">York Town</placeName> to enquire into the matter. 
          Four Irishmen were apprehended at <placeName ref="#us_me_pemaquid" role="direct">Pemaquid</placeName> by the 
          Sheriff and committed for trial at the next General 
          Sessions. They acknowledged that they assisted in 
          seizing Grover's schooner, and said that they had orders 
          to do so from Alexander Hamilton, Captain of the 
          Fort. When the Sheriff came near Pemaquid, he 
          saw the colours flying at the fort, and being informed 
          by some Irish people that they designed to resist him, 
          he sent a message to the officer there that he came 
          with authority to apprehend some criminals etc. and 
          required his assistance, who answered that he would 
          keep his fort and did not admit the Sheriff etc. The 
          guns were loaded, but the messenger warned the officer 
          that if he went on, they would every one be hanged. 
          Upon which Hamilton said he would take advice with 
          his Council, and went out of the fort, and the Sheriff 
          entered without opposition etc. Copy. 11 pp. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>6.2</num><date when="1730-12-12">Dec. 12, 1730</date></dateline>
        <p>Robert Auchmuty to Governor Belcher. <placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="direct">Boston</placeName>,
          12th and 14th Dec., 1730. Gives his recollection of 
          the conversation between the Governor, Col. Dunbar 
          and himself at the Governor's house on 4th Oct., 
          which was carried on with all the loyalty and harmony 
          possible. No such words were used as that the King's 
          Instructions signified nothing, or that the King had 
          not an acre to the westward of <placeName ref="#rv_stcroix" role="boundary">St. Croix</placeName> etc. Signed, 
          Robt. Aukmuty. 3| pp. \C.O. 5, 898. Nos. 78, 
          78 i, ii.] </p>
      </div>  
      <div>
        <dateline><num>7</num><date when="1731-01-12">Jan. 12</date></dateline>
        <p>Order of Committee of Privy Council. Referring back 
          to the Council of Trade and Plantations their report upon the 
          petition of Lord Percival etc. for establishing a charitable 
          Colony in <placeName ref="#us_sc" role="direct">S. Carolina</placeName>, to consider the alteration proposed by 
          petitioners, after hearing them thereupon etc. Signed, Temple 
          Stanyan. Endorsed, Reed., Read 13th Jan., 173. l pp. 
          Enclosed, 7. i. Alteration proposed by Petitioners in above report. 
          In lieu of words to lay before H.M. lists of all such 
          officers .... under their Common Seal, the words, 
          Under their common Seal to constitute Courts of 
          Record and other Courts to be held in H.M. name, 
          and for the space of 21 years to appoint and displace 
          all officers civil and military within the said district 
          together with such other powers as have been granted 
          on the first establishment of Colonys. If pp. [C.O. 
          5, 362. ff. ll-12v., 180.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>8</num><date when="1731-01-12">Jan. 12</date></dateline>
        <p>Memorial of three Justices of <placeName ref="#ca_nl" role="direct">Newfoundland</placeName> to 
          Governor Osborn. Copy of C.S.P. 1730, Sept. 25 end. iv. 
          Signed, Wm. Keen, Wm. Weston, A. Southmayd. Endorsed, 
          Reed, (from Capt. Osborn), Read 12th Jan., 173f 1 p. [C.O. 
          194, 9. ff. 67, 681;.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>9</num><date when="1731-01-12">Jan. 12</date></dateline>
        <p>Queries by Governor Osborn. To desier the opinion 
          of Council touching the power of the Fishing Admirals in 
          persuant to the Act of Parliament. Whether the Fishing 
          Admiral's power and Civill Majestrates interfere in any respect, 
          and wether the former have any power to send warrants to 
          constables, comit to prison, or command the stock, or wether 
          they ought not to be subordinate to the latter. Whether the 
          Justices of Peace may not act in <placeName ref="#ca_nl" role="direct">Newfoundland</placeName> by the Statu 
          laws of this Kingdom. Whether I have not the power of a 
          Justice of Peace and sett at their Quarter Sessions, or other 
          meetings by virtue of my commission. Endorsed, Reed., Read 
          12th Jan., 173$. | p. [C.O. 194, 9. ff. 70, 70.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>10</num><date when="1731-01-12">Jan. 12</date></dateline>
        <p>Mr. Popple to Mr. Fane. Requests his opinion upon 
          the preceding Queries<placeName ref="#ca_nl" role="direct"></placeName>. Encloses Governor Osborn's copies of 
      Commission and that given by him to Justices of the Peace. 
      [C.O. 195, 7. pp. 254-256.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>11</num><date when="1731-01-12">Jan. 12</date></dateline>
        <p>Council of Trade and Plantations to the Duke of 
          Newcastle. Enclose copies of Governor Hunter's letter etc. 
          1st Oct., 1730. Autograph signatures. 1 p. Enclosed. Extracts referred to in preceding. [C.O. 137, 47. 
          ff. 79-85 ; and (without enclosure) 138, 17. p. 307.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12</num><date when="1731-01-12">Jan. 12</date></dateline>
        <p><placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="secondary">Boston</placeName>. Col. Dunbar to Mr. Popple. Refers to former letters. 
          Continues : As to my disputes with the New Engld. people 
          I hope I shall be justifyed ; if ever any body was among them 
          without disputes, I will own myself in the fault and submit to 
          be sacrificed to their resentment ; since their Committee was 
          at <placeName ref="#us_me_frederick" role="direct">Fredericksfort</placeName> I have been threatened with many actions 
          of trespass, and even high treason for building a fort and hoisting 
          the King's colours, wch. they themselves prostitute at their 
          little pallisadoed truck houses to exchange rum, molasses, and 
          tobacco etc. with the Indians ; I landed here the 10th instant 
          haveing been 12 days in my passage from Fredericksfort ; I 
          was in great danger by islands of ice in the <placeName ref="#rv_kennebec" role="direct">river of Kennebeck</placeName>, 
          but I was obliged to go into that river to stop some saw mills 
          there who were destroying a fine swamp of pine trees near ye 
          water upon lands wch. I have reserved for the Royal Navy in 
          case the Proprietors or claimts. are disallow'd by H.M. etc. I 
          could not avoyd makeing some appointments of lands within 
          10 miles of the fort, where people are clearing ye woods, and 
          converting the timber, wch. is oak, birch, ash, maple and 
          popple, to ship timber, cord wood, and for pottash, and in order 
          to plant corn, garden seeds, hemp and flax in the spring, if I 
          had not done so, of course all would have dispersed, and would 
          never be induced to return, so that <placeName ref="#us_ne" role="direct">New England</placeName> would boast 
          of a victory, than which nothing could be a greater mortification 
          to me ; I have not presumed to make any grant, or exercise 
          any sort of jurisdiction, tho' many applications have been 
          frequently made to me in small cases, as a Governour or 
          Majestrate ; I dare not have refused hearing ye partys, then 
          gave my opinion, complaining it was hard upon me, haveing 
          no assistce. to be troubled with little disputes, and desired they 
          might either defer matters or agree among themselves until 
          majestrates could be appointed, and thus I have satisfied the 
          people, and kept them together, but if after all, they must quit 
          and loose their labour, many familys will be undone, and I 
          the unhappy occasion of their misery, as I am at this time of 
          my own ruine and my familys by my zeal and perseverance to 
          promote this settlement, because I am convinced beyond all 
          doubt that it will be very considerable and satisfactory to H.M. ; 
          I send to my Lords Commissioners a smal parcel of hemp and 
          flax, the produce of new ground at Fredericksfort of this year 
          and from New England seed, the seed wch. I had from <placeName ref="#pl_danzig" role="indirect">Dantzick</placeName> 
          by way of <placeName ref="#en_london" role="indirect">London</placeName>, being treacherously kept concealed until 
          the season was over ; I wish I had a fund to send for some of 
          each this year, and for two or more potash makers to <placeName ref="#pl" role="indirect">Poland</placeName> 
          or <placeName ref="#ru" role="indirect">Russia</placeName>. I think I could promise to serve <placeName ref="#en" role="indirect">England</placeName> with 
          those commoditys in return for their manufacturys without 
          bringing away any of their mony, it is seldome any poor man's 
          scheme is worth anything, however hints may be usefull to 
          great ones ; I ought to be sufficiently discouraged as no notice 
          is ever taken from any of the Offices of my letters, yet I live in 
          hopes, wch. onely supports my spirits. These small samples 
          of hemp and flax, are not in such perfection as they would be 
          had I been at the place in time ; ye person I chiefly depended 
          upon to pull and dress them went away being discouraged by 
          common reports, an Irishwoman pulled, water-rotted and 
          dressed the flax, and the hemp was in the grownd when I arrived 
          there in the end of October, so that it was dew-rotted and even 
          frozen as it stood, the man who dressed it as you see it, has 
          made ropes and geer for cattle and carriages of some of it, and 
          assures me it is very strong, and undertakes to make it of as 
          fine a colour as flax next year, he tells me ye hemp here will 
          be finer than any European and has a good deal of the soft 
          nature of flax etc. From Kennebeck I went to <placeName ref="#us_me_portland" role="direct">Casco</placeName>, where 
          there is onely one loading of masts provideing this year, the 
          rest being contracted for at <placeName ref="#us_nh_new_castle" role="direct">Piscatua</placeName>, wch. I am glad of in 
          respect to the Province of <placeName ref="#us_nh" role="direct">New Hampshire</placeName> who are generally 
          a loyal good sort of people ; I went to ye undertakers house for 
          ye contract, and shewed him the orders I reed, to prevent 
          logging, he insisted on his right not to be interrupted, and 
          alleddged that he logged on his own private property etc. Refers 
          to enclosed letters which passed between them. Continues : Near 
          his house wch. is built in the woods and upon grownd cleared 
          within three years past, are five new mills each saw can cut 5 
          and sometimes 6000 feet of pine boards in 24 hours, he told me 
          if I sho'd stop his mills it would be ten pounds pr. diem damage ; 
          the lands about Casco are generally called private property, 
          and not one owner of a mill there but was pleased with the easy 
          proposal I made them to prove their property. I hope I am 
          not blameable for this condescention, and besides I am of 
          opinion yt. few or none of them will be deemed good ; some 
          shewed me their titles wch. were patents passed by Sir Edmd. 
          Andros in 1688, wherein are reserves of wheat and mony to 
          the Crown as an annual quit-rent, when I took notice of those 
          reservations, and sayd I would acquaint H.M. therewith, they 
          then disdained those titles, and sayd they did not esteem them, 
          for that they had some old titles from Sir Ferdinando Gorge 
          and Indian deeds ; I asked why they would produce Sir Edmond 
          Andros's pats, to me, they replyed because they seemed best to 
          the eye, but that it was an imposition of his to extort mony 
          from the people. Upon enquiry I find there are very many of 
          those patents, and all register'd, and if no quit-rent has been 
          received since, wch. is payable to H.M. or His Capt. Genii, of 
          the <placeName ref="#us_ma" role="indirect">Masachusets</placeName>, it will amount to a considerable sum, and 
          may easily be recovered after a reform in this Governmt., wch. 
          I hope is now upon the anvil. What I am now speaking of is 
          in the large county of York, formerly called the <placeName ref="#us_me" role="indirect">Province of 
          Maine</placeName>, 90 miles along the sea coast and backwards to ye South 
          Sea in the original grant ; My Lords Commrs. may think 
          that country is settled and peopled, whereas 20 miles in length 
          and halfe so much in width would be sufficient for them ; there 
          is yet onely one line of towns layd out there and they extend 
          all along the shore and onely eight miles backwards into the 
          country, thus many many millions of acres lye wast, whilst 
          these gentry are opposeing H.M. to make other parts usefull 
          to the Crowne ; if such matters are not represented home, no 
          remedy can ever be applyed ; this country not content with all 
          this ; do claim most part of <placeName ref="#ca_ns" role="indirect">Nova Scotia</placeName>; it is this stragling 
          manner of settlement has (with their natural ill treatment of 
          all persons) allways exposed them to the insults of the Indians, 
          which (besides many poor souls cutt off), has cost them a great 
          many thousand pounds, and all might have been prevented by 
          gentle usage and some small present yearly to the poor natives, 
          who, unprovoked, seem a good natured people ; I herewith 
          send you a complaint from a Jesuit at one of their tribes 
          settlemt., to whom I wrote in English hearing he was an Irish 
          or Scotchman ; I hope by his influence to secure the friendship 
          of his tribe. Acknowledges receipt of H.M. Additional 
          Instruction for giving his share of the penalties upon loggers 
          to informers. Will endeavour to prevent any abuse of that 
          indulgence etc. Continues : I likewise received (Sunday, 10th 
          Jan.) an office pacquet for Governour Belcher, with which I 
          went to wait upon him, and he being ingaged at dutys (as they 
          call them) I sent it by a gentleman on Monday morning, and 
          wrote to him that some reasons to which he was no stranger 
          prevented my waiting upon him, one of wch. was, the threats 
          of the mobb etc. Encloses his answer, (encl. i). Continues : 
          It is wonderfull how this great man and generally his country- 
          men can act and say, and deny both. His behaviour and useage 
          of me is beyond my imagination, and tho' to my face he denyed 
          many things, I could prove them by many wittnesses, his last 
          stroke is most provokeing of all, he has given out here that I 
          was a spy in <placeName ref ="#es" role="indirect">Spain</placeName> and was so here now upon him and the 
          country. I hope as he is not comeatable here my Lords will 
          think I ought to have some satisfaction for so gross an abuse, 
          one consequence of it had likely to have fallen lately upon 
          Capt. Protheroe, Commander of ye Station ship, who walking 
          in ye street, a man enquired of another who he was, answer 
          was made, Collo. Dunbar, whereupon one replyed God d n 
          him lett us mobb him, but being undeceived, the Capt. escaped ; 
          I came onely hither to attend the Courts upon account of the 
          expences I was unawares drawn into last year at Fredericks- 
          fort, and here mett the additional trouble of the return of 500/. 
          sterl. bills drawn by me on my groweing sallary wch. are pro- 
          tested. I intend in a few days to New Hampshire and into the 
          woods, and to send one of my Deputys to remain at Casco. 
          You no doubt have all the proceedings of this Great and General 
          Court transmitted by his Excy. to my Lords, no Governour 
          was ever more hated than he, and notwithstanding any assure- 
          ances he may give to the Ministry of succeeding in getting a 
          fixed sallary from the new Assembly, everybody tells me it 
          never will be given to him, and his pretences are onely to spin 
          out time, and keep the affair out of Parliament. I am even 
          told that the country have soe great an abhorrence of him for 
          betraying them (as they call it) that many of the first rank 
          are upon an Address to H.M. to give them any other Governr. 
          and they will comply with the Instructn. His chief Councilour 
          and favourite is the famous incendiary Dr. Cook, whose character 
          is known at home, and both the Govr. and Doctor irreconcileable 
          enemys to ye Dudley family who are reputed ye chiefs 
          of this country ; they were allways for the sallary and the 
          favourite Cook ever against it, wch. seems unaccountable that 
          a Governour is in earnest, and caresses the man, who is at 
          the head of his opposers. My Lords have heard of Govr. 
          Wentworth's death of New Hampshire, he was a worthy honest 
          gentleman, and is much lamented by the country, it is worth 
          nothing to be Leiut. Governour, who has no sallary but 200/. 
          this country mony, which all chief Governours before Mr. 
          Belcher gave out of their 200/. sterl., and he would not give a 
          shilling, nor is that small province able to give any ; they are 
          apprehensive that Mr. Belcher has recommended one Mr. 
          Waldron to be Lt. Govr., who was Clerk to the Council, 
          and is so now and yet is made a Councillour and a Judge by Mr. 
          Belcher, who has made great changes there, heavy upon gentle- 
          men who were putt in by Mr. Shute and Mr. Burnet for their 
          dutyfull and cheerfull complyance wth. ye Royal instructions. 
          Mr. George Jaffrey is one of them, he is of the Council, was one 
          of the Judges, and Treasurer of the Province, and Vice- judge 
          of the Admiralty, he is a man of good sense, fortune and figure, 
          and much the fittest to command that Province, I believe he 
          would accept of it, tho' I really do not know, but this I am sure 
          that no man there is more disaggreable to the King's friends than 
          Mr. Waldron. I was exceedingly surprised upon my arrival 
          here two days agoe to hear that Govr. Belcher had closetted 
          Mr. Auchmuty the Advocate General and prevailed upon him 
          to give a strange turn and construction to the conference he was 
          wittness to, wch. I gave my Lords an account of by my brother. 
          I taxed the Advocate Genii, with it who swore to me it was 
          false, and that he omitted nothing but the Governour's telling 
          me of sending down 500 men to dismantle the fort and take 
          the people prisoners, he promised to send me a copy of what 
          he gave Mr. Belcher, and to add that circumstance to it, wch. 
          he sayd had escaped his memory, but I rather take it he did it 
          out of complemt. to His Excellency. Mr. Auchmuty has told 
          ye story as I related it to my Lords Commrs., in twenty 
          places in this town etc. Continues : I am informed that many 
          heads here are now at work plodding against me. I defye all 
          the world whilst they stick to truth, but they would do anything 
          to have me removed etc. I am this moment told that there is 
          a Council sitting upon the report of the tryal of the four poor 
          men, brought from near Fredericksfort by order of this General 
          Court fr. the High Sheriffe of the county of York in October 
          last, it is sayd they are convicted but I am not able to learn for 
          what crime etc. I told you formerly they had onely stoped a 
          sloop from taking away some staves cutt by themselves. The 
          Governour wanted to try them for piracy. Pray Sir, Lay this 
          before my Lords etc. Signed, David Dunbar. Endorsed, Reed. 
          16th March, Read 13th Oct., 1731. Holograph. 14 pp. 
          Enclosed, </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.1</num><date when="1731-01-12">Jan. 12</date></dateline>
        <p>Governor Belcher to Col. Dunbar. <placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="indirect">Boston</placeName>, Jan, 12, 
        1731. Acknowledges packet. " If you had inclined 
        to have come with it yourself, I am a stranger to any 
        reasons why you did not etc" Does not believe he is 
        in the least danger from the mob, and would protect 
        him, if there should be any appearance of that etc. 
        Signed, J. Belcher. Endorsed as preceding. 1 p. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.2</num><date when="1730-12-30">Dec. 30, 1730</date></dateline>
        <p>Jacques Siresme, Jesuit Priest <placeName ref="#us_me_norridgewock" role="direct">among the Abnaquis</placeName>, 
        to Col. Dunbar. 30th Dec. (N.S.), 1730. Acknow- 
        ledges letter and looks forward to visiting him in the 
        spring. Does not understand English. Is surprised 
        that he makes no mention of religion etc. Signed, 
        Jacques Siresme, Jesuite etc. Two letters, one in Latin, 
        one in French. The whole endorsed as preceding. 2 pp. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.3</num><date when="1731-01-26">Jan. 26</date></dateline>
        <p>Robert Auchmuty to Col. Dunbar. <placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="indirect">Boston</placeName>, 26th 
        Jan. 1730. Makes good the omission in his account 
        of the conference between Col. Dunbar and Governour 
        Belcher, as described in covering letter. Signed, 
        Robt. Auchmuty. 1 3/4 pp. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.4</num><date when="1730-10-12">Oct. 12, 1730</date></dateline>
        <p><placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="indirect">Boston</placeName> Gazette, Oct. 12th, 1730. Numb. 567. 
        With a notice of Col. Dunbar that he has warned the 
        people he found cutting white pine trees in <placeName ref="#rv_sheepscot" role="direct">Sheepscot</placeName> 
        or Sheepsgut river that he had included that place 
        among the 300,000 acres of timber to be reserved in 
        <placeName ref="#ca_ns" role="indirect">Nova Scotia</placeName> for trees for the Royal Navy etc. Printed. 
        2 pp. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.5</num><date when="1731-01-27">Jan. 27</date></dateline>
        <p>Major Cope to Jerr. Dunbar. <placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="indirect">Boston</placeName>, 27th Jan., 
        1730. The chief occasion of Governor Philips' ordering 
        me to this place was the prospect of engaging severall 
        French Protestant families, to goe (agreable to their 
        own propositions) and settle in <placeName ref="#ca_ns" role="direct">Nova Scotia</placeName>, being 
        disapointed in that view, shall return to <placeName ref="#ca_ns_annapolis_royal" role="direct">Annapolis Royall</placeName>,
        not well pleas'd " etc. Comments on the two 
        letters (encl. i and iii) which have come to his hands 
        etc. The latter shows that the conversation between 
        Col. Dunbar and Governor Belcher amounted to the 
        full to what the former wrote Col. Tayler on 12th Nov. 
        (v. C.S.P. 17th Nov.), 1730 etc. Signed, Hen. Cope. 
        Holograph. 3 pp. 
        
        12. vi. Copy of correspondence betwen Col. Dunbar and 
        Lt. Gov. Tailer. v. C.S.P. 17th Nov., 1730. 4 pp. 
        Enclosures iii-vi, endorsed as covering letter. [C.O. 217, 
        6. ff. 39-46, 47, 48, 48u., 49z;., 50z;.-54, 55-56v., 570.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.7</num><date when="1731-01-07">Jan. 7</date></dateline>
        <p>Col. Dunbar to Mr. Westbrook. <placeName ref="#us_me_portland" role="direct">Casco</placeName>, Jan, 7, 
        1730 (1731). Reply to following. 
        " You desire me to shew you and your workmen 
        such trees as we have remarked fit for H.M. use. That 
        wood be an imployment for us all and of course neglect 
        our duttyes in other parts " etc. But will appoint 
        a deputy to attend him, though it is contrary to what 
        he objected last year. " My brother was with you 
        great part of that winter and has yr. letter by way of 
        certificate how effectually he prevented the destruction 
        of the timber on <placeName ref="#rv_saco" role="direct">Saco River</placeName>, which I find you have 
        forgot " etc. Signed, David Dunbar. Endorsed, 
        Reed. 16th March, Read 13th Oct., 1731. 3 pp. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.8</num><date when="1731-01-06">Jan. 6</date></dateline>
        <p>Col. Westbrook to Col. Dunbar. 6th June [sic], 
        1730/1. Desires his assistance, according to Instructions, 
        in selecting trees for the Navy under Ralph Gulston's 
        contract. Much timber up <placeName ref="#rv_saco" role="direct">Saco River</placeName> was cut and 
        destroyed last fall by permission of his deputy. " But 
        behold when yr. brother come to inform you of it no 
        man like him to be imployed in them parts to take 
        care of ye King's interest etc. I have great reason to 
        beleive you have continued this officer of yrs. with 
        some private veiws to damnify my interest and 
        intercept Mr. Gulston in his complying with his contract 
        etc. Signed, Tho. Westbrook. Endorsed as preceding. 
        Addressed. 1 p. [C.O. 5, 873. ff. 139-140u., 143, 143v.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>12.9</num><date when="1730-02-23">Feb. 23, 1730</date></dateline>
        <p>Thomas Westbrook to Col. Dunbar. <placeName ref="#us_me_scarborough" role="indirect">Scarborough</placeName>. 
        23rd Feb., 1729/30 . Reports rumour of his death. His 
        brother came in the nick of time to save the timber 
        at <placeName ref="#rv_saco" role="direct">Saco Falls</placeName>, " which I inform you of when I was in 
        <placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="indirect">Boston</placeName>. Saveing some trees which was cut about 
        two months afore we got there, and just as we got 
        there. There was six teams going up in the road and 
        some of them had just begun to fall and had fallen 10 
        or 11 trees which your brother markt " etc. Signed, 
        Tho. Westbrook. Addressed. | p. [C.O. 5, 873. ff. 142, 142.]</p> 
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>13</num><date when="1731-01-13">Jan. 13</date></dateline>
        <p><placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="secondary">Boston</placeName>. Governor Belcher to the Council of Trade and 
        Plantations. Repeats gists of covering letter, Jan. llth, and 
        refers to those enclosures. Adds : These things, my Lords, 
        are the whole of what I have ever done respecting <placeName ref="#us_me_frederick" role="direct">Frederick's 
        Fort</placeName> etc., and how was it possible for me to do less ? I inclose 
        your Lordships a memorial I deliver'd into H.M. Secretary of 
        State the 15th May last, in answer to which I should have been 
        very glad of some orders or directions for my conduct, but never 
        receiv'd a word of answer till his Majesty's order in Council of 
        12th Novr. last. According to the clause of the Charter cited 
        in my memorial these lands My Lords are doubtless a part of 
        this Province, and agreeable thereto your Lordships will find 
        in H.M. Commission to me these words, " And the lands lying 
        between the said territory of <placeName ref="#ca_ns" role="indirect">Nova Scotia</placeName>, and the <placeName ref="#us_me" role="indirect">Province of 
        Main</placeName>." Quotes Commission to show that it makes the Charter 
        " the great rule of my Government " etc. Continues : How 
        dare I then disobey H.M. or betray the trust he has repos'd 
        in me by refusing a legal protection to his good subjects, when 
        they apply to me. These rioters, My Lords, have been since 
        legally convicted in H.M. Courts, and must doubtless undergo 
        the penalties of the law for such a breach of H.M. peace, and so 
        notorious an assault and riott committed upon the property, 
        and liberty of H.M. good subjects. I am here, my Lords, H.M. 
        Govr. to see a good execution of all his wholsome laws for 
        the safety of his subjects under my care in their lives and 
        estates, and to this end I will endeavour carefully to use the 
        power the King has delegated to me in his Royal Commission 
        etc. Continues : It is false in Col. Dunbar to say, No private 
        persons have hitherto set up any claim on those lands, because 
        there have been a great many claims made, and are made daily, 
        and the people that claim think they have a just right (tho' 
        not by any grant of this Province) and one of the men whom 
        Coll. Dunbar's people riotted and assaulted has a claim there 
        descended down to him for 105 years past as may be seen in 
        his complaint against these notorious riotters. My Lords, 
        every man's private property is his life, and I can't answer for 
        people's giving away what they think their own. But for the 
        right of this government to those lands according to the Royal 
        Charter. Had Coll. Dunbar wisely manag'd about 'em I think 
        I should have had influence enough with this Assembly to have 
        made a cession of their right to the Crown : and it was always 
        my opinion that it wou'd be greatly to the advantage of this 
        Province, that the Crown should settle those lands. Yet etc. 
        I know not how to answer those that say, The Crown has always 
        supposed these lands to be a part of this Province, or why have 
        the Govrs. of the <placeName ref="#us_ma" role="indirect">Massachussetts</placeName> been ordered from time 
        to time to insist with the Assemblies to rebuild the Fort at 
          <placeName ref="#us_me_pemaquid" role="direct">Pemaquid</placeName>. They say why have not the Governours of <placeName ref="#us_nh" role="indirect">New 
        Hampshire</placeName> and Nova Scotia had those Instructions, and again 
        the King has directed the choice of a Councellour in the Royal 
        Charter to be chosen on account of those lands, and who of 
        course becomes one of the Legislators of H.M. Province of the 
        Massachusetts Bay, and without such a Councellour the present 
        Constitution cannot subsist. My Lords, I should be glad, I 
        say, to be instructed how to answer these things etc. Concludes : 
        I am tired of writing as I fear your Lordships will be of 
        reading, yet I must not be so vilely traduc'd and not answer 
        for myself ; I am an honest man, and hope ever to appear so. 
        Nor cou'd I possibly have done more from my arrival to this 
        day, than I have, in support of H.M. Dominions as well as for the 
        welfare of the Provinces under my care etc. Signed, J. Belcher. 
        Endorsed, Reed. 23rd Feb., Read 9th June, 1731. 7| pp. 
        Enclosed,</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>13.1</num><date when="1730-05-15">May 15, 1730</date></dateline>
        <p>Memorial of Governor Belcher to the King. 15th 
        May, 1730. Has received accounts from <placeName ref="#us_ne" role ="indirect">New England</placeName> 
        that Col. Dunbar hath made settlements on lands 
        lying between the <placeName ref="#rv_kennebec" role="direct">River of Sagadehock</placeName> and the <placeName ref="#gf_stlawrence" role="direct">Gulph 
        of St. Lawrence</placeName>, which the <placeName ref="#us_ma" role ="direct">Province of the Massa- 
        chusetts Bay</placeName> apprehend to be part of the lands of that 
        Province and not to be alienated but by grant from 
        them according to the Royal Charter etc. quoted. Asks 
        for plenary instructions how to conduct himself in this 
        affair, and that Col. Dunbar may in the mean time be 
        directed to withdraw from those lands, and forbear 
        any further proceedings, till the right be fully deter- 
        mined etc. Signed, J. Belcher. Endorsed, Reed. 23rd 
        Feb. 173. Copy. 2 pp.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>13.2</num><date when="1730-05-15">Dec. 29, 1730</date></dateline>
        <p>Proclamation by Governor Belcher. <placeName ref="#us_ma_boston" role="direct">Boston</placeName>, 29th 
        Dec., 1730. For preventing the destruction of the 
        woods in the <placeName ref="#us_ma" role ="direct">Massachusetts Bay</placeName>, and publishing H.M. 
        Additional Instruction relating thereto, 26th Sept., 
        1730. Signed, J. Belcher. Endorsed as preceding. 
        Printed by B. Green. 1 p. [C.O. 5, 872. ff. 170- 
        175v., 17Gv.-177v., 178v.-179v. (with abstract).]</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>14</num><date when="1731-01-13">Jan. 13</date></dateline>
        <p>John Southall to the Duke of Newcastle. Encloses 
        following scheme, " wch. I hope may be of advantage to H.M. 
        Island <placeName ref="#jm" role="direct">Jamaica</placeName> and to <placeName ref="#gb" role="indirect">Great Brittain</placeName>, and as the same may be 
        put in execution without expence to any and can't but prove 
        of profit and advantage to all, I wish it may meet with appro- 
        bation " etc. Offers to give further explanations and to " make 
        a draught of the island to show where and how long each road 
        ought to be " etc. Signed, Jno. Southall, living at the green 
        posts in the green walk near ye faulcon <placeName ref="#en_southwark" role="secondary">Southwark</placeName>. 3/4 large p. 
          Enclosed,</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline><num>14.1</num><date when="1731-01-13">Jan. 13</date></dateline>
        <p>Some considerations on the present state of the Island       
        <placeName ref="#jm" role="direct">Jamaica</placeName>, 1st In regard to its imminent danger from 
        the slaves in rebellion, 2dly in regard to that island's 
        past and present very great scarcity of provisions. 
        Proposes the construction of roads, every inhabitant 
        supplying his every sixth negro for that purpose etc. 
        The rebel negroes would then have to surrender, and, 
        amounting to 10,000 could be sold at 201. a head to 
        pay expences and for maintaining forts etc. The 
        mountainous woods at present occupied by the negroes 
        or unoccupied would then supply abundance of game 
        and provisions. Also it is well known there have been 
        veins of gold and silver ore found in the blew moun- 
        tains, which the dread of the negroes alone prevents 
        being explored etc. 2| large pp. [C.O 137, 53. ff. 
        297-298U.] </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>